Medford Historical Society Collection of Civil War Photographs MS267
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Medford Historical Society Collection of Civil War Photographs
circa 1861 -- 1907
circa 1861 -- 1865
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Medford Historical Society (Medford, Mass.)
MS267
49.85 Linear Feet 46 boxes
The Medford Historical Society Collection of Civil War Photographs contains photographs of Civil War subjects, including landscapes and studio portraits of soldiers and veterans.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were placed on deposit by the Medford Historical Society in February 2020, accession MS-2020-060.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series: General Samuel C. Lawrence's Civil War photo collection and the Medford Historical Society Civil War collection.
Biographical / Historical
General Samuel Crocker Lawrence (1832-1911) was commander of the Lawrence Light Guard during the Civil War and the first Mayor of the City of Medford in 1895.
Custodial History
The majority of the collection was amassed by General Samuel Crocker Lawrence (1832-1911). On General Lawrence's death, the collection passed into the custody of the Light Guard, and in 1948 Colonel John J. Carew of the guard and Mrs. U. Haskell Crocker, General Lawrence's granddaughter, donated the photographs to the Medford Historical Society.
Materials in Series 2, the Medford Historical Society Civil War collection, were compiled by members of the Grand Army of the Republic (G.A.R.) Post 66 (S.C Lawrence) and were also donated to the Medford Historical Society by Carew in 1948.
Other Finding Aids
This collection has been digitized in its entirety by the Digital Commonwealth. Please see
https://www.digitalcommonwealth.org/collections/commonwealth:4b29gp26z.
Scope and Contents
The Medford Historical Society Collection of Civil War Photographs contains photographs of Civil War subjects, including landscapes and studio portraits of soldiers and veterans. The majority of the materials are albumen prints. Formats also include an ambrotype, autographs, collodion prints, engravings, lithographs, montages, mounted cabinet card photographs, a tintype, and a photomechanical print.
Medford/Somerville history; Civil War; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Medford Historical Society (Medford, Mass.)
- General Samuel C. Lawrence's Civil War photograph collection, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000001; 40.04 Linear Feet 40 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photographs of Civil War subjects, including landscapes and studio portraits of soldiers, collected by General Samuel C. Lawrence.
  - Images 0101-0106, 0405, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000002; 7 Items (Box 1)
    Open for research.
  - Images 0331-0365, 0897, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000003; 36 Items (Box 1A)
  - Images 0391-0398, 0236, 0366, 0420, 0421, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000004; 12 Items (Box 2)
  - Images 0422-0425, 0433-0448, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000005; 20 Items (Box 3)
  - Images 0203-0208, 0237-0251, 0426-0432, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000006; 28 Items (Box 4)
  - Images 0167-0193, 0403, 0404, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000007; 29 Items (Box 5)
  - Images 0120-0148, 0399, 0400, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000008; 31 Items (Box 6)
  - Images 0621-0650, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000009; 30 Items (Box 7)
  - Images 0367-0390, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000010; 24 Items (Box 8)
  - Images 0449-0479, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000011; 31 Items (Box 9)
  - Images 0480-0494, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000012; 15 Items (Box 10)
  - Images 0537-0546, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000013; 10 Items (Box 11)
  - Images 0252-0264, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000014; 13 Items (Box 12)
  - Images 0301-0330, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000015; 30 Items (Box 13)
  - Images 0495-0504, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000016; 10 Items (Box 14)
  - Images 0505-0536, 0899, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000017; 33 Items (Box 15)
  - Images 0107-0119, 0201, 0202, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000018; 15 Items (Box 16)
  - Images 0265-0266, 0268-0300, 0401, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000019; 36 Items (Box 17A)
  - Images 0149-0166, 0267, 0402, 0898, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000020; 21 Items (Box 17B)
  - Images 0194-0200, 0215-0228, 0406, 0413, 0414, 0419, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000021; 25 Items (Box 18)
  - Images 0547-0561, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000022; 15 Items (Box 19)
  - Images 0562-0582, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000023; 21 Items (Box 20)
  - Images 0583-0597, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000024; 15 Items (Box 21)
  - Images 0598-0620, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000025; 23 Items (Box 22)
  - Images 0651-0684, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000026; 34 Items (Box 23)
  - Images 0685-0714, 0728, 0901-0904, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000027; 35 Items (Box 24)
  - Images 0715-0727, 0729-0744, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000028; 29 Items (Box 25)
  - Images 0745-0777, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000029; 33 Items (Box 26)
  - Images 0778-0794, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000030; 17 Items (Box 27)
  - Images 0795-0826, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000031; 32 Items (Box 28)
  - Images 0827-0841, 0900, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000032; 16 Items (Box 29)
  - Images 0842-0865, 0896, 0905-0907, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000033; 28 Items (Box 30)
  - Images 0908-1366, 1583-1613, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000034; 490 Items (Box 31)
  - Images 0001-0054, 0056-0100, 0209-0214, 0229-0235, 0407-0412, 0415-0418, 0866-0895, 1367-1582, 1614-2027, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000035; 782 Items (Box 32)
  - Images 2028-2846, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000036; 819 Items (Box 33)
  - Images 2902-2994, 2996-3601, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000037; 699 Items (Box 34)
  - Images 2847-2875, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000038; 29 Items (Box 35)
  - Images 2876-2883, 2886-2892, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000039; 15 Items (Box 36)
  - Images 2893-2901, 2995, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000040; 10 Items (Box 37)
  - Images 3602-3696, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000041; 95 Items (Box LCW)
- Medford Historical Society Civil War collection, circa 1861 -- 1907; MS267.000042; 9.81 Linear Feet 6 boxes
  This series consists mainly of montages, as well as some photographs of veterans, related to the Civil War.
  Custodial History
  These materials were collected by members of the Grand Army of the Republic (G.A.R.) Post 66 (S.C Lawrence) and were donated to the Medford Historical Society by Colonel John J. Carew Carew in 1948.
  - Images 001-152, circa 1861 -- 1907; MS267.000043; 152 Items (Box GAR 1)
  - Montages 1948.6.001-036, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000044; 36 Items (Box 1)
  - Montages 1948.6.037-070, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000045; 34 Items (Box 2)
  - Montages 1948.6.071-103, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000046; 33 Items (Box 3)
  - Montages 1948.6.104-134, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000047; 31 Items (Box 4)
  - Montages 1948.6.135-159, circa 1861 -- 1865; MS267.000048; 25 Items (Box 5)